Tiago Pateiro

(+351) 912 600 769 • tiago.mpateiro@gmail.com • LinkedIn • Homepage

Software Engineer

Excellent team member, multi-disciplinary and assertive **developer** with 9 years of progressive experience in several business areas in both consultancy and product management. My core skill sets are programming languages alongside with information systems with proven capacity to adapt to new challenges. I'm endlessly curious and tech passionate as I'm always looking to increase my knowledge and keep up to date with new trends. I've always been fascinated with ways of handling large amounts information, how to provide better access to it, make it more meaningful and semantically searchable to improve the user experience and knowledge access by everyone.

My areas of expertise include:

Software Development • Web Development • Front-End Development • R&D • Algorithms • Databases • Reporting/Visual Analytics • Data Extraction Tools • Business Processes • Data Analytics

Professional Experience

DefinedCrowd Lisbon, Portugal

Lead Software Engineer Software Engineer

January 2020 – Present July 2019 – December 2019

Fast growing Portuguese artificial intelligence start-up aiming to provide high quality data to its clients in a crowd sourced approach. Leveraging machine learning technology and human intelligence to source, structure, and enrich high quality training data in speech, NLP and computer vision.

Integrated in *human-in-the-loop* cluster, responsible, as technical lead, for the increase of the crowd engagement through e-learning, gamification and experience approaches in order to provide truly certified crowd to the available tasks in order to match the requirements and increasing the quality of executed tasks. Through optimization and following segmentation techniques, provide crowd to our clients that are engaged and matching their requirements.

Key Contributions: NDA

Main Technologies: C#.NET, React, TypeScript, .NET Core, Docker, Azure, HTML5/CSS3, SQL Server, Spark, Druid, Kafka, Python (Data Science), Superset

Truphone SCNL Lisbon, Portugal

Software Engineer

August 2017 - June 2019

London based Telecommunications Company that aims to increase connectivity regardless the country in the world. Either for M2M (IoT) or regular user it seeks a world without borders.

Integrated in the Machine-to-Human team based in Portugal responsible for the client facing/customer experience products at Truphone. Hired to be part of an inter-disciplinary team to assess the requirements of the stakeholders regarding mobile applications, portals, web applications and decide the best technology stacks and/or architecture to implement such user stories adding value to our customers who represent more than 60% of the income.

Key Contributions: NDA

Main Technologies: C#.NET, Node.JS, React/React-Native, TypeScript, .NET Core, MongoDB, Elasticsearch, Docker, HTML5/CSS3, Gulp, SQL, Java (Spring), Spark

Salon and Spa Ultimate

Lisbon, Portugal

Full Stack Developer

January 2016 - August 2017

Fast growing market reference software solution for the Salon and Spa industry across the United States. Provides software management solutions to help the daily basis of the salons (POS software) as well as analytics and web management features of the business itself.

Hired to integrate the development team based in Portugal to implement several features to enhance the existing solution and keep increasing the business value of the customers. As well as provide know-how on the research and designing of these key features keeping in mind the user experience, performance and scalability.

Key Contributions:

- Online booking system built an integrated and scalable booking platform to be used as standalone website
 or inside the customer's websites to allow their clients to book appointments, select stores geographically,
 pick services, providers, etc. This solution allowed the salons to save money since no investment is needed
 in some custom booking feature as it is, also, already connected to the management software.
- Central Management Core platform to help the daily functions of the salon's managers. It provides the ability to push down to several deployments' common features of the business such as promotions, inventory products, users, clients, roles, etc. This feature increased the productivity of managers for large chains since it provided a way to perform single operations and propagate them to the entire group.
- Reporting Contributed with previous experience in BI solutions to build a data warehouse with relevant metrics and reports to increase the business value taken by the managers.

Main Technologies: Node.JS, Backbone.JS, React, TypeScript, .NET Core, EF Core, PHP, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Docker, AWS, HTML5/CSS3, Gulp, Sequelize.JS, SQL, C#.NET

ROFF Lisbon, Portugal

Developer

March 2012 – January 2016

Portuguese SAP Gold Partner Consultancy firm leader in the Portuguese market in SAP solutions. Provides know-how to their clients to improve their operations and business processes using SAP ERP software. Based in several countries, the client base includes several foreign markets.

Recruited to integrate the near shore development team based in Lisbon to develop the technical aspect of several core business operations. Including the integration with external software solutions in different technologies/frameworks.

Key Contributions:

- Quality Management module designed the API to provide the needed endpoints to integrate the SAP QM module with *OutSystems* used on the touchscreens used in the client's laboratories as well as leading the SAP team. Also built several reports and approval workflows for samples analysis in SAP system. These features significantly increased productivity and a better control by the persons in charge and also to save in terms of paper consumption.
- Warehouse Management solution using several SAP technologies for WM participated in the implementation of warehouse management systems where the forklift trucks would receive notifications on where to pick the items and where to leave them. Contributed with some algorithms for best path to optimize the driver's operations
- Excel SAP Integration contributed with some Excel add-ins in order to provide custom formulas that would retrieve data from SAP systems by consuming several web services.
- Automatic Production Entries designed a custom solution based on client's request acting in the Olive Oil
 industry to automatically calculate the split the production cost among several cost centers and the profits.
 Contributing to the increase of their worker's productivity since no manual calculation would be needed
 after the produced goods.

Main Technologies: C#.NET, SQL, SAP ABAP, Excel Add-Ins, Javascript (UI5)

InspirennovIT Almada, Portugal

Developer

September 2011 – March 2012

Growing Portuguese startup providing several custom solutions to the public sector using Microsoft solutions.

Hired to be part of the R&D team to analyze and design solutions to increase the productivity in public sector mainly in administrative roles.

Key Contributions:

Digital Signatures of documents – implemented an application to visualize the documents in PDF format,
place the signature in the document as well as sign them with the Portuguese citizen card. The signed
document would be submitted to SharePoint and go to the next approver in the workflow increasing the
productivity and decreasing the process time.

Main Technologies: .NET MVC, C#.NET, EF, SQLServer, SQL, Sharepoint, HTML/CSS, Javascript

Faculty of Sciences and Technology - UNL

Almada, Portugal

Research Grant Holder

September 2011 – March 2012

Research Center

Collaborating with other MSc students to build a data warehouse system that would hold academic information and future candidates. This would allow the institution to get relevant metrics, analyze the results of several courses and subjects as well as taking decisions based on those reports to increase the quality of the various departments.

Key Contributions:

- Access to candidates' information developed a tool to retrieve, from external sources, information about the candidates such as their living area, average, institutions options, etc.
- Geographic aggregator contributed with clustering algorithms to build metrics based on geographic information as well as reporting plugins to visualize this data.

Main Technologies: SQL, MySQL, Pentaho BI, Java

Education

MSc in Knowledge Management and Information Systems

ISCTE-IUL, 2016 - 2018

Data Mining • Data Visualization • Data Science • Knowledge Management • Big Data • Machine Learning

Postgraduate in Computer Science

Faculty of Science and Technology – New University of Lisbon, 2010 – 2012

Data Warehousing • Mobile Computing • Database Management • Semantic Web • Advanced Algorithms

Awards:

Best Data Warehousing Project

BSc in Computer Science

Faculty of Science and Technology – New University of Lisbon, 2006 – 2010

Distributed Systems • Algorithms and Data Structures • Software Engineering • Human Machine Interaction

Awards:

Best Final Project (Geographical Academic Platform)

Technical Skills

Javascript • C# • NodeJS • HTML5 • CSS3 • React/React-Native • Typescript • .NET Core • Python (including Data Science libraries) • Entity Framework • Sequelize • SQL • Java • WebAPI • Gitlab Pipelines • Git • Docker

Hobbies and Interests

Swimming • Trail • Basketball • IoT devices • Technology • Self-taught programming